In this module, we're going to discuss UNIX processes along with program execution, pipes
and threads, and let's get started by asking what are the functions and interfaces for
ZOS UNIX system services.
The XPG 4.2 API is defined in a set of standards from the open group.
This API defines some general operating system functions as well as some functions that
are specific to a UNIX system.
Functions which conform to XPG 4.2 UNIX are fully supported by the UNIX System Services
or USS API.
The XPG 4.2 functions are defined in terms of C language bindings.
When a ZOS UNIX program requests a system service, the following events take place.
First of all, the application programmer codes a C language statement with a function request,
for example, fork.
Fork requests that a new process be created.
During compilation of the program, a section of code called a stub is included in the compiled
module.
When the program is run, the stub identifies the runtime library or the RTL routine corresponding
to the fork function and passes control to this routine.
For some functions, the service can be performed by the library routine itself.
For others such as fork, the library routine includes a call macro instruction that selects
the appropriate callable service to request by name.
The callable service named BPX1FRK in turn calls the appropriate ZOS service function.
And finally, the ZOS UNIX kernel performs the requested service.
The XPG 4.2 kernel is a ZOS address space which is started at IPL time and initialized
with system parameters in a sys1.palmlib member.
All files are allocated to the kernel and all IO operations result in calls to the kernel.
Interactive users of ZOS UNIX services can log on to TSOE and issue the command OMVS.
The OMVS command schedules a local process, which is FPR, which shares the TSO address
space.
Additional address spaces can be created by shell commands.
The workload manager, or WLM, is used to start these address spaces.
Users attached to ZOS through a TCPIP network can use the R login or telnet capability to
enter the ZOS system.
Their identity is checked and a shell address space is created for them.
Additional address spaces can be created for them by the workload manager for their shell
commands.
ZOS provides support to allow an installation to re-customize and re-initialize the ZOS USS
environment without re-IPLing the system.
The FOMVS comma shutdown operator command, along with the FOMS comma restart operator
command, can be used to shutdown and re-initialize the USS environment.
A process is created to run a program and associated resources to the program.
In ZOS UNIX a process resides in an address space and that is the basic unit of work
that runs within that address space.
A process is created by another process or by a request for a ZOS UNIX service.
A process that creates a new process is called a parent process and the new process is called
a child process.
A child process can be created by the fork callable service.
A process is identified by a process ID or a PID and it is associated with its parent
process by a parent process ID or PPID.
There are different types of processes.
There's user processes which are associated with the user program or a shell user.
Kernel processes perform system functions for the kernel and daemon processes perform
continuous or periodic system functions.
To get information about ZOS UNIX processes the shell command PS can be used.
A ZOS UNIX user can use this command to display information about all the active processes.
A super user can display information about all the processes in the system by using
the command PS minus uppercase A. PS is a very useful command when finding processes
and handling them.
COMVS, ASID equals NNN or A equals NNN displays process information for the specified hexadecimal
address space ID or ASID.
If the specified ASID is not a ZOS UNIX system services address space an error message will
be issued.
The operator can display the status of a particular OMVS process and its threads with the following
command D OMVS comma PID equals and then the process ID.
This shows information about each thread of a multi-threaded application.
The thread ID would be needed to cancel an individual thread.
There are several ways to stop a ZOS UNIX process.
One option is the operator modify command.
The term option allows the signal interface routine to receive control before termination.
The force option prevents the signal interface routine from receiving control before the
process is terminated.
A special option shut down equals fork in it can be used to bring down the system cleanly.
Be aware it cancels all current BPX-AS address spaces created as a result of spawn or fork.
The kill shell command can be used to cancel a process.
A user can cancel their own processes and a system administrator or a super user has authority
to kill other users' processes.
Term sends a SIGTERM signal and kill sends a SIGKILL signal.
And the ZOS cancel command can be used to cancel an address space that contains a ZOS
UNIX process.
If the address space contains multiple processes, cancel causes all of them to terminate.
UNIX System Services Processes is new.
Type PS to access the Processes panel, which allows authorized users to display information
about ZOS UNIX processes.
You can then use the command C to cancel the process and D to display information about
the process.
Use PRE, short for prefix, or other filters to limit the rows displayed to some processes.
Use ARR for Arrange to place interesting columns on the first panel.
Or on Job Name to keep rows from jumping around.
Next up, we're going to ask, what is a demon?